Don't forget about me!
We're both women,
so don't mock me!
《サクラ : 私だっているんだ。
同じ女なら バカにしないで！》
Naruto... Sasuke... Sakura!
《カカシ : ナルト サスケ サクラ…。
You guys make
a nice picture right now.
うん いい画だ。
今のお前らは…。
I really love you guys!
大好きだ》
Now!
Shannaro!
(サスケ)今だ！
しゃ～んなろ～！
All right!
(ナルト)よっしゃ～！
Six Paths Planetary Devastation!
(２人)六道地爆天星。
To think that I,
the originator of chakra...
《カグヤ : またしても→
このチャクラの祖である わらわが→
would be defeated by pieces of
my own chakra, again...
このような分散したチャクラどもに
敗れるとは…》
Why?!
《カグヤ : なぜだ!?》
Hmm? They've done it!
《ハゴロモ : フッ やりよったか。
All that's left is to bring
you all back!
あとは お前たちを
連れ戻すだけだ》
うっ！ ぐぅ～！
グォ～！
Is the ground being
sucked up towards her?
うわっ！
大地が 吸い寄せられているのか!?
We finally made it out!
(孫)やっと出られた。
Kurama, your Jinchuriki's pretty good.
九喇嘛 やるな お前の人柱力は。
(九喇嘛)フン…。
オオ…。
グォ～！
aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
Once again, shine upon you
Congratulations
Over here!
こっちだ！
Sasuke!
What happened to Naruto?
サスケ君！
ん？ ナルトはどうした？
He went off by himself,
saying there was something
he had to take care of.
やり残していることを
片づけてくると 一人離れた。
More importantly, we need to
get farther away from here!
それより ここから
もっと遠くへ離れろ！
At this point, it can't be helped.
I'll just start over and work on
Mother's next resurrection!
(ゼツ)こうなってはしかたない。
また次の母復活へ向け…。
That reminds me,
you don't like being separated
from your mom, right?
そういや お前
親離れしたくねえんだったな。
D-Damn you!
き 貴様！
I haven't forgotten about you.
Hiding in the shadows
and creeping around for all this time!
今までずっと陰に隠れて
コソコソしてたお前のことだって→
見逃しゃしねえよ。
グッ お前など！
You!
You're just a piece of
the shinobi history I created.
ただ俺の作った
忍の歴史の一部！
A brat like you could never...!
お前のようなガキに 俺は…。
History?
歴史？
Shinobi history...
忍の歴史っつうのは→
consists of all sorts of ninja's lives,
and deaths!
いろんな忍者の生きざまと
死にざまだ。
Many shinobi taught me
what it means to be a shinobi.
俺は いろんな忍者から→
忍ってのが なんなのか
教えてもらった。
The pain and sadness of death...
the tragedy of war.
人の死の悲しみや
戦争の悲惨さ…。
And not only that!
They taught me the joy of
being accepted and being loved!
それだけじゃねえ。
認めてもらえる嬉しさに
愛される喜びもだ！
The way they lived...
and the way they died...
みんなの生きざまが 死にざまが
俺に教えてくれたんだ！
made me who I am!
They taught me and trusted me!
俺に託していったんだ！
You're a brat who
can't even leave the nest!
親離れもできねえ ガキ１人が
勘違いしてんじゃねえってばよ！
Get over yourself!
うわ～っ！
ぐわ～っ！
It's still growing.
It's like a moon.
(カカシ)まだ 大きくなってる…。
まるで 月のようだな。
Guys!
(サクラ)あっ！
It's over.
みんな！
終わったな。
The seal is complete!
We can finally celebrate!
封印 終了！
これで めでたし めでたし
だってばよ。
You're right.
そうなのね。
The first thing I want is a hot bath
う～ん… まずは お風呂に入って
汗と汚れを落として→
to wash away all
this sweat and grime.
Hold on a sec!
What about us?!
さっぱりしたいわね。
How are we supposed to
get out of this Time-Space?!
って… 私たちは どうすんの!?
Oh no! You're right!
This is bad! This is bad!
この空間から
どうやって戻るのよ!?
He does whatever
needs to get done.
あぁ～っ！ そうだった!!
But he's still pretty dumb, isn't he?
やることは やる。
だが 少々 アホだな やはり。
Summoning Jutsu!
口寄せの術！
ん？ ん？
Welcome home, Naruto.
(ミナト)おかえり ナルト。
Dad...
父ちゃん…。
Naruto, who's this?
Six Paths Super Gramps!
ナルト… この人 誰？
Which means...
六道の大じいちゃん。
That's right,
you're back in your world
これってば…。
through a Summoning performed
by all prior Five Kage together.
そうだ 戻ってきたのだ。
かつての五影 皆で
口寄せの術をしてな。
I called all of
the previous Five Kage
(ハゴロモ)歴代の五影に
協力してもらうよう→
from the afterworld to help.
わしが 浄土から呼んだのだ。
Naruto, Sasuke...
and the rest of you...
ナルト サスケ… そして みんな。
Excellent work saving the world.
よくぞ 世界を救ってくれた。
Six Paths Super Gramps?
Are you by any chance
the legendary...?
六道の大じいちゃん？
I am Hagoromo Otsutsuki.
もしかして あなたが 伝説の…。
Also known as
the Sage of the Six Paths.
わしは 大筒木ハゴロモ。
通称 六道仙人と呼ばれておる。
No wonder... you're levitating.
At this point,
nothing shocks me anymore.
でしょうね… 浮いてるし。
It seems like everything
went well.
ここまでくると もう
びっくりするのも 疲れちゃった。
The Shinobi World sure went to
hell while we were dead.
どうやらよ
うまくいったようじゃねえのよ。
死んどる間に 忍の世界も→
Damn it!
It's the first time I've seen so many
Tailed Beasts together in one place!
大変なことになっとるな
まったく…。
The Sage of the Six Paths, eh...
尾獣が ここまで揃うのを見るのは
初めてだな。
It feels like we've wandered
into a fairy tale!
六道仙人か…。
So you are the one, after all.
まるで おとぎ話の中に
迷い込んだようよ。
Summoning the past
Five Kage here and...
(カカシ)やはり そうでしたか。
being able to bring the Tailed Beasts
and us back from the other Time-Space...
先代の五影様を呼び寄せたり→
You're probably the only person
who could perform such godly actions.
あの空間から
我々を尾獣ごと呼び戻したり…。
こんな神がかったことが
できるのは→
Are you Kakashi Hatake?
あなただけでしょうから。
Oh... yes.
Good job guiding everyone and
sealing my mother away.
お前が はたけカカシだな？
あ… はい。
(ハゴロモ)よくぞ 皆を導き
母を封印してくれた。
That truly was the work of gods.
Oh, no.
I hardly played any part at all.
これこそ 神の御業よのう。
いえ 私はほとんど
何もできませんでした。
It was these three
and many comrades.
こいつらと
多くの仲間のおかげです。
And... a former friend also
lent me strength.
それに かつての友が
私に力を貸してくれましたから。
That's why I said you
guided everyone well.
だから 言った
よくぞ 皆を導いたと。
Despite losing your way,
you remained Naruto's teacher
and Obito's friend.
お前は迷いながらも
ナルトたちの師で→
Or else, you likely wouldn't have
succeeded in stopping my mother.
オビトの友であり続けた。
でなければ 恐らく母は
止められなかったであろう。
Hey! Kurama!
Were you lonely being
separated from me?
お～い 九喇嘛！
I missed you!
俺と離れて寂しくなかったか？
Don't talk so loud!
I wasn't lonely.
会いたかったぜ。
You have half of me
inside you... remember?
でけえ声出して呼ぶな
寂しくなんかねえよ。
わしの半分は
そっち入ってんだろうが。
Just look at Kurama,
all embarrassed and flustered!
アハハハ。
フフフ。
But this is exactly
what I had once envisioned.
あの九喇嘛が恥ずかしがって
慌てておるわ。
だが これこそ
わしが思い描いたもの。
That there would one day
be a shinobi,
who could move even
the Tailed Beasts to cooperate.
尾獣たちすら
自ら 協力したくなる。
そういう忍が現れたのだからな。
Even Obito was Naruto's doing...
オビトのことも 本当は ナルトが…。
He restored Obito.
彼が オビトを戻してくれた。
I see...
Then I shall ask Obito to tell me
that tale in the afterworld.
そうか なら その話はあの世で
オビトに詳しく聞くとしよう。
Is he still...?
ん？ 彼はまだ…。
I'm gonna get going soon.
Yeah...
(オビト)そろそろ行く。
I really made a mess out
of the Shinobi World.
そうか。
俺は忍の世界を
ムチャクチャにしてしまった。
So much that I don't even know
what to say to you before I go.
いまさら何を言って→
去っていったら
いいのかもわからない。
We're able to say goodbye
as friends, not enemies.
To the old you...
最後は敵でなく
友として別れができる。
the one who was always late
because you were helping others.
人助けばかりで遅刻していた
あの頃のお前とな。
That's plenty enough for me.
俺にとっては それだけでいい。
Thanks, Kakashi.
(オビト)ありがとな カカシ。
I'll be going then.
じゃあな もう行くよ。
I've been keeping Rin waiting.
リンを待たせてっから。
Do you have an excuse ready?
(カカシ)
遅刻の言い訳は考えてあるのか？
I told her beforehand
I'd be helping you.
お前を助けてくるって
前もって言っといた。
I see...
そうか。
Same here...
Thank you, Obito.
《カカシ : こっちこそ…。
ありがとな オビト》
Kakashi Sensei!
Sakura... Thank you.
カカシ先生！
Kakashi Sensei, your eyes!
あ… サクラ すまない。
Yeah...
はっ カカシ先生
目が…。
As of today, Kakashi of
the Sharingan is no more.
ああ 写輪眼のカカシも
今日で終わりだ。
Madara was a Jinchuriki.
Even if it was temporary...
emptied of the Tailed Beast,
he won't last long.
マダラは一度 人柱力となった。
It's his fault for trying
to use such things.
尾獣たちが抜けた今
助からん。
Sasuke, Naruto...
そんなものを利用するから
ああなる。
Behold, the end of
your predecessors.
サスケ ナルト。
You should watch this closely.
お前たちの前任者の最後だ。
見ておくといい。
Is that you, Hashirama?
(マダラ)柱間… か？
(柱間)うむ。
I guess neither you,
nor I could achieve what we wanted.
お前も… 俺も…。
望んでも 届かない…
ものだな…。
It's never that easy!
Our job is to do all that we can,
while we're alive.
そう簡単にいくか。
And then, bequeath the rest for
future generations to accomplish.
俺たちの生きてる間に
できることはしれてる。
だから託していかねばな。
So naïve...
先の者がやってくれる。
as usual.
相変わらず… 甘いな。
You... were always... the optimist.
フフフ。
お前は いつも…
楽観的だった。
But perhaps...
that is the correct path.
だが それが
正しいのかもしれんな…。
My dream...
was squashed.
俺の夢は ついえた。
But your dream...
still lives on.
だが… お前の夢は
まだつながって… いる。
We were both too hasty.
We didn't need to fulfill
our dreams ourselves.
急ぎすぎたな。
It was more important to cultivate
those who would come after us...
俺たちは届かなくても
よかったのだ。
to whom we could entrust
our dreams.
後ろを
ついてきてくれるもの→
託せる者を育てておくことが
大切だった。
Which means I would
have failed anyway.
なら俺は無理だったって…
ことだ。
Since I always hated someone...
standing behind me...
後ろに立たれるのが
嫌いだった… からな。
When we were kids...
You once said we're shinobi
and we don't know
when we'll die.
ガキの頃 お前は
俺たちは忍で→
And that for neither side to die,
いつ死ぬかも
わからぬと言った。
we'd both have to reveal
what's inside of us
互いに死なぬ方法が
あるとすれば→
and pour each other drinks
to toast like brothers.
敵同士
腹の中を見せ合って→
兄弟の杯を
酌み交わすしかねえと。
But we're both about to die.
Right now, we can drink together,
as war buddies.
だが もう互いに死ぬ。
今なら ただ戦友として
酒を酌み交わせる。
War buddies... huh?
戦友… か。
Well...
I guess... that's okay...
まあ… それなら…。
by...
俺… たちも…。
This is the perfect moment.
I will release the jutsu,
free the Five Kages
頃合いだな。
and those under the Reanimation.
五影たちも
穢土転生たちも→
わしが解術する。
Go.
行ってこい。
Dad...
Oh, that's right.
I've been meaning to tell you...
父ちゃん。
そうだ… 言っとかなきゃなって
思ってたんだ。
えっ。
Happy birthday!
誕生日おめでとう。
You've become
a splendid young man, Naruto
本当に立派になったね ナルト。
Yeah... Thank you.
We're an existence outside
of the rules.
うん サンキュー。
We can't remain
in this world forever.
俺たちは外法の存在。
It's time to say good-bye.
いつまでも
ここにいるわけにはいかない。
お別れだ。
I promise to tell
Kushina everything.
クシナに いろいろ伝えておくよ。
Tell her not to worry.
I'm eating properly!
俺ってば ちゃんと飯食ってっから
大丈夫だって言ってくれ。
I'm not picky and eat
lots of different stuff!
Like, tonkotsu ramen,
miso ramen, and shoyu ramen...
好き嫌いしねえで
いろいろ食べてんだ。
Oh but, not just ramen though!
え～と とんこつに
味噌に しょうゆに…。
I try to bathe every day!
あ！
ラーメンばっかじゃねえよ もちろん。
I go to the Leaf Hot Springs
once in a while too!
あ～ 風呂も ほぼ毎日入ってるし。
Although everyone just says
I only take quick dips...
たまに 木ノ葉の温泉行くし。
みんなには烏の行水とか何とか
言われてっけど ハハッ。
What else, what else...
I've made lots of friends!
それから えっと えっと…。
And they're all good guys!
And...
友達は いっぱいできたんだ。
みんな いいやつなんだ。
I was really awful at school,
but I never got depressed and
それから 勉強はまったく
うまくいかなかったけど→
had more confidence
than anyone else!
まったく落ち込まないっていう
自信っつうのかな。
Naturally, I always obeyed
それは 誰よりあったんだよね。
Lord Third and Kakashi Sensei.
もちろん
三代目やカカシ先生の言うことも→
I respect them both!
They're right here,
so you can ask them yourself!
ちゃんと聞いてたぞ。
尊敬してるし。
Oh! And those
Three Prohibitions of Shinobi?
あっ ここにいるから
直接 聞いてもいいってばよ。
I learned a lot about that
when I was with Pervy Sage!
あぁ それと
忍の三禁ってやつ？
He was hopeless
when it came to them though...
エロ仙人についてたときに
いろいろ勉強になったってばよ。
but he was
an awesome Sannin
三禁についちゃダメダメだったけど→
and I respect him the most!
エロ仙人は
三忍としちゃ かっけえ忍で→
I just turned 17 today,
いちばん尊敬してんだ。
so I don't know much
about alcohol or girls...
俺ってば
今日17歳になったばっかだから→
I know Mom said to find
someone like her...
酒も まだよくわかんねえ。
ただ 母ちゃんは→
But... that's... um...
母ちゃんみたいな女を
見つけろって言ってた。
けど… それは えっと…。
Anyways!
Not everything
Mom told me about went well,
とにかく 母ちゃんの言ったこと
全部うまくいってねえけど→
but I'm doing the best I can!
I've got dreams too!
I'm gonna become an even
greater Hokage than you, Dad!
そこそこ頑張ってんだ！
夢だって ちゃんとある。
I swear I will!
俺ってば
父ちゃんを超す火影になる。
ぜってえなるからな！
So when you see Mom over there,
please tell her...
that she doesn't have to
worry about me at all!
Tell her I'm doin' my best!
Got it...
I'll make sure
to tell her everything.
boku ni wa wakaru nda uso o tsuite iru kimi ga
I can tell when you're lying
naite ii yo koko ni zutto irukara
It's okay to cry because I'll always be here
sekaijuu ni koborete iru hontou no ai no kimochi
Feelings of true love spills out throughout the world
sagashidashite miushinatte yoake ga kuru no matteru
We search for it but lose it, while waiting for daybreak
migi no hoshi ni wa boku no namae o tsukete
The star on the right will bear my name
kimi ga yonde okureyo
Will you call out to it?
hidari no hoshi ni wa kimi no namae ga ne
The star on the left will bear your name
niau yo zutto soba ni irukara
It's perfect, because we'll always be together
Having fought
my mother Kaguya...
Is there any change to
the answers you gave me?
My answer's the same.
Now then, Sasuke...
What about you?
あっちで
母ちゃんにも伝えてくれ。
Yes, but first...
俺のことは
全然 心配なんかすんなって。
the current Five Kage inside
the Infinite Tsukuyomi...
しっかり やってんだって！
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"The Final Valley"
わかった。
What did you just say, Sasuke?!
全部しっかり伝えておくよ。
うっ… うぅ…。